Hello.
We refer to the lifelong habits that we form as karma, also known as "Karmic Consciousness.
These lifelong habits are extremely difficult to change.
These include, not only habits of our bodies such as eating and sleeping, but also habits of our thinking.
We should change some of these habits, but it's difficult to do so because of the tremendous resistance that follows.
It's similar to the resistance you feel when you are trying to quit smoking.
I recently read in a scientific journal that our brain activities are wired to perceive things negatively.
Maybe our brains are wired for being unenlightened.
The study claimed that the brain is structured for negative perception.
I am not sure if that's 100% accurate.
I personally think that it's a problem of software instead of hardware,
Most of us do perceive things negatively.
If you see negative perception as karma of the unenlightened, you can say that positive perception is the mind of the Bodhisattva.
Changing the habit of negative thinking to that of positive thinking can be called practice, cessation of karma, or changing one's fate.
Practive is changing the way we think instead of changing the environment. Changing the way we perceive things.
It's seeing both sides of things simultaneously instead of just one side.
If you see only one side of something, you can't understand it completely, so what you say about it cannot be right.
We call this ignorance.
Practice is not about making a person become aware of things who is completely unaware of.
He thinks he knows something, but he doesn't have complete understanding because he is only looking at one side.
If a blind man touches a leg of an elephant, he concludes that it is like a pillar. Since he experienced the elephant in his own way, he claims that he knows what an elephant looks like. However, that's not true.
Seeing things completely, from all side, is like opening the eyes.
We call this, insight.
This insight is also called wisdom.
If you can see one side as well as the other side, you are no longer angered by or hate things that used to before; and you discover positive aspects about things you used to view negatively.
This is the reason why we practice.
Practice has little to do with being a Buddhist or a Christian.
Fundamentally, Buddhism transcends religion.
It is not one of the religions since it transcends them.